Register of the Albert Glotzer papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- Trotskyist Period Papers, 1928-1940
  - Internal documents, 1930-1940, undated
    - 1934 (Folder 9: 9)
      Includes statement and resignation of Antoinette Konikow group; "The League and the New Party" with proposed amendment by Hugo Oehler; motions on France by Martin Abern; resolution on organic unity by Jack Weber; "Proposed Declaration of Principles for New Party"; "The Next Step of the Communist League" and "To Influence Revolutionary Events or to Bark at Them" by Albert Goldman; resolution on organizational report by James P. Cannon, Arne Swabeck and Max Shachtman
    - 1935 January-June (Folder 10: 1)
      Includes reply to Leon Trotsky by Hugo Oehler; "The Party after the Pittsburgh Plenum"; outline of organizational considerations by Martin Abern; "The Situation in the Party" by A. J. Muste and Jack Weber; resolution on attitude toward Socialist Party and Communist Party; resolution on international relations; draft resolutions by A. J. Muste, James P. Cannon, Max Shachtman, Hugo Oehler and others
    - 1935 July-December (Folder 10: 2)
      Includes statements by Nathan Gould, A. J. Muste, Max Sterling, Jack Weber and others; "Draft Memorandum on the Significance of the 'French Turn'"; resolution on the internal party situation; "The War Situation"; draft statement on developments in Socialist Party by A. J. Muste, Jack Weber and others
    - Undated, circa 1934-1936 (Folder 10: 3)
      Includes resolution on the Negro question by Hugo Oehler and others; other resolutions by Hugo Oehler, Tom Stamm and others; "Problems of the Trade Union Movement"; resolution on the situation in the Soviet Union by Max Shachtman; report on the New York City committee by Martin Abern; "Position and Perspectives of American Imperialism"; "Building the American Section of the Fourth International"; "What Is Our Problem?" by James Burnham; draft resolutions on Latin America
    - 1936 (Folder 10: 4)
      Includes statement on Workers Party of the United States convention by A. J. Muste, Martin Abern and Maurice Spector; summary of discussions with Leon Trotsky on the American question; "Maritime Strike, West Coast" by Tracy Adams
    - Undated, circa 1936-1937 (Folder 10: 5)
      Includes "Statement on the International Question"; resolution on labor party
    - 1937 (Folder 10: 6)
      Includes "Revolutionary Class Struggle vs. the People's Front"; circular letters by James Burnham, James P. Cannon, Joseph Carter, Emanuel Geltman, Max Shachtman and Maurice Spector; "The Politics of Jack Altman" by James Burnham; Toledo branch document on unemployment question; "Conflicts in the Chicago Organization" by James P. Cannon; "The Most Group: A Study in Political Pathology"; resolution on the Soviet Union by Joseph Carter; "The Crisis in the Socialist Party"; "American Labor Party and the Labor Party"
    - 1938 (Folder 10: 7)
      Includes circular letters by James Burnham, James P. Cannon and others; "The Death Agony of Capitalism and the Tasks of the Fourth International"; "For a Revolutionary Socialist Party" by Glen Trimble; "The Fourth International in Europe"; reply by F. X. Ferry to statement by Glotzer
    - Undated, circa 1937-1939 (Folder 10: 8)
      Includes "The Present War in the Far East and the Tasks of Our Party"; "Draft Thesis on the Minnesota Farmer-Labor Party"; circular letter on Minnesota Farmer-Labor Party by Vincent R. Dunne; resolution on youth
    - 1939 January-August (Folder 11: 1)
      Includes circular letters by James Burnham, James P. Cannon, Albert Goldman, Max Shachtman and others; summary of discussions with Leon Trotsky on work within the Communist Party; constitution of the Socialist Workers Party; resolution on Negro work; resolution on maritime policy
    - 1939 September-October (Folder 11: 2)
      Includes circular letters by James P. Cannon and others; "The U.S.S.R. in War" and "On the Question of the Defense of the USSR" by Leon Trotsky; "Resolution on the Soviet Union in the Present War" and "Report on the Russian Question" by Max Shachtman; "The Defense of the USSR and the Present Imperialist War" by C. L. R. James; "Shall We Revise the Slogan of Unconditional Defense?" by Albert Goldman; "Speech on the Russian Question" by James P. Cannon; statement by Martin Abern
    - 1939 November-December (Folder 11: 3)
      Includes circular letters by James P. Cannon and others; "The Defense of the U.S.S.R. in the Present War" by Lebrun; joint statement on party unity; "A Petty-Bourgeois Opposition in the Socialist Workers Party" by Leon Trotsky; "What Is at Issue in the Dispute on the Russian Question" by Martin Abern and others; "The War and Bureaucratic Conservatism"; "The Soviet Invasion of Finland"; "Resolution on the Soviet-Finnish War"
    - Undated, circa 1939-1940 (Folder 11: 4)
      Includes "On the Character of the War, and the Perspectives of the Fourth Internationalists"; "Our Strategy in the Soviet Union in the Present War: For Revolutionary Defeatism, for the Third Camp" by Joseph Carter; "The Roots of the Party Crisis" by C. L. R. James; "Resolution on the Organization and Tasks of the Party"; "The Trade Union Movement, and the Immediate Tasks of the Party in the Development of Mass Work"
    - 1940 January (Folder 11: 5)
      Includes circular letters by James P. Cannon and others; "The Fourth International and the Russian Question" by Sam Gordon; "The Crisis in the American Party" by Max Shachtman; "The Politics of Desperation" by James Burnham; "Shamefaced Defensism" by Dwight Macdonald; New York local activity bulletins
    - 1940 February (Folder 12: 1)
      Includes "Science and Style" by James Burnham; "The Cannon Line in Practice" by B. J. Widick; "Who Is Preparing a Split?" by Albert Goldman; "Correspondence with Comrade Trotsky" by Martin Abern; "From 'Science' to Slander" by Joseph Hansen; "Back to the Party!" by Leon Trotsky; "The Discussion in Minneapolis" by Max Shachtman; "Minnesota Answers the Minority" by Grace Carlson and others; "The Second World War and the Soviet Union"; New York local activity bulletins
    - 1940 March 4-12 (Folder 12: 2)
      Includes "The Truth about the Auto Crisis" by George Clarke; "Not in Our Name!" by Leon Trotsky; "An Answer to the Splitters"; "Concerning Johnson" by James P. Cannon; "On Organizational Methods"; "The Soviet Union as a Big Trade Union, or How a Cannonite Argument Becomes a Boomerang" and "Socialist Democracy or Bolshevik Mythology?" by Joseph Carter; "Where Is the Petty Bourgeois Opposition?"; "Cannon Organizes the Split under the Cry of 'Stop Thief!'"
    - 1940 March 15-27 (Folder 12: 3)
      Includes "A Bankrupt Opposition Bloc" by Jack Weber; "An Open Letter to Johnson" by Albert Goldman; "The Judgment of Events"; "Who Has Been Preparing a Split in the Party?"; "A Little Note on Statesmanship"; "Letter to Comrade Rork" by Lebrun; "The Abern Clique" by Joseph Hansen
    - 1940 April (Folder 12: 4)
      Includes "'Unity Proposals' or Cover for Split?"; circular letter by Max Shachtman; "The Results of the Convention"
  - Internal instructional materials, circa 1930s
    - Educational bulletins, circa 1930s (Folder 12: 5)
    - Class outlines for Marx-Lenin School and International Workers School, circa 1930s (Folder 12: 6)
      Includes The ABC of Marxism (two versions); The Truth about Kronstadt by John G. Wright; Theses and Resolutions Adopted by the Second Congress of the Comintern
  - Public issuances, circa 1930s
    - Socialist Appeal. Vol. 2 no. 12 (1936 December 15), vol. 3 no. 2-3 (1937 February-March), 1936-1937 (Folder 13: 1)
    - Miscellany, circa 1930s (Folder 13: 2)
      Article from The Militant on Farmer-Labor Party; flyers and leaflets
    - Bibliographies, circa 1930s (Folder 13: 3)
      Includes lists of articles by Albert Glotzer in Socialist Appeal and The Militant
  - Youth affiliate records, 1931-1940, undated
    - Minutes, 1931-1936
      - 1931 October-December (National Youth Committee, Communist League of America) (Folder 13: 4)
      - 1932 January-December (National Youth Committee, Communist League of America) (Folder 13: 5)
      - 1933 March-October (National Youth Committee, Communist League of America) (Folder 13: 6)
      - 1934 March-December (Spartacus Youth League) (Folder 13: 7)
      - 1935 January-December (Spartacus Youth League) (Folder 13: 8)
      - 1936 January (Spartacus Youth League) (Folder 13: 9)
    - Internal bulletins, circa 1930s (Folder 13: 10)
      International Youth Bulletin no. 1 (1934) [Spartacus Youth League]; Educational Bulletin no. 1 (1935) [Spartacus Youth League]; Educational Outline no. 1 (1935) [Spartacus Youth League]; International Information Bulletin unnumbered issue (1935) [Spartacus Youth League]; Socialist Youth vol. 2 no. 2 (1938) [Young People's Socialist League (Fourth International)]
    - Minutes, 1931-1936
      - 1932-1934 (Folder 13: 11)
        Includes draft resolution on the question of war; declaration and motion at 1932 Student Congress against War
      - 1935 (Folder 13: 12)
        Includes circular letters by Nathan Gould; declaration to and reports on American Youth Congress by Reva Craine and Nathan Gould
      - 1936-1940 (Folder 13: 13)
        Includes circular letters by Emanuel Geltman and Nathan Gould; resolution on 1940 Socialist Workers Party dispute
      - Undated, circa 1930s (Folder 13: 14)
        Includes report on Student Congress against War; open letters to Young People's Socialist League and Young Communist League; "Fascism and the Youth"; resolutions on Spain, the international situation, and expulsion of Walter Held from the International Bureau of Revolutionary Youth Organizations
  - International affiliate records, 1931-1940, undated
    - Minutes, 1931-1936
      - 1931 February-October (International Left Opposition) (Folder 13: 15)
      - 1932 July-December (International Left Opposition) (Folder 13: 16)
      - 1933 August-December (International Left Opposition; International Communist League). Also includes minutes of the Conference of Four meeting between International Communist League and Dutch and German parties (Folder 13: 17)
      - 1934 April-June (International Communist League) (Folder 13: 18)
    - Internal bulletins, 1930-1937
      - 1930 (Folder 13: 19)
        Bulletin International no. 1 (International Left Opposition--French edition); Internationales Bulletin no. 2 (International Left Opposition--German edition)
      - 1931 (Folder 14: 1)
        International Bulletin no. 1-3, 5-9/10 (International Left Opposition--English edition)
      - 1932 (Folder 14: 2)
        Internationales Bulletin no. 13-19 (International Left Opposition--German edition)
      - 1933 (Folder 14: 3)
        International Bulletin no. 17 (International Left Opposition--English edition)
      - 1934 (Folder 14: 4)
        International Bulletin new series no. 1-2 (International Communist League--English edition)
      - 1936 (Folder 14: 5)
        Theses, Resolutions, and Appeals of the First International Conference for the Fourth International (International Secretariat for the Fourth International)
      - 1937 (Folder 14: 6)
        Information Bulletin unnumbered issue (International Bureau for the Fourth International--English edition)
    - Internal documents, 1931-1937
      Circular letters, reports, discussion bulletins, resolutions, memoranda, flyers, and leaflets
      - General, 1931-1937 (Folder 14: 7)
        Includes circular letters by Rudolf Klement, M. Mill, Hugo Oehler and Leon Trotsky re "French turn" and other matters; report by M. N. Trent on the 1936 International Conference for the Fourth International; open letter by Natalia Sedova re arrest of Sergei Sedov; declaration to Geneva Anti-War Congress; resolution on American section; "Declaration on the Necessity and Principles of a New International" by Conference of Four parties; "Frey as 'Historian'" by Jan Frankel
      - Belgian section, 1934-1935 (Folder 14: 8)
        Includes circular letters and reports by Leon Trotsky and Georges Vereecken
      - Brazilian section, 1934 (Folder 14: 9)
        Circular letter by Brazilian section
      - British section, 1931-1938 (Folder 14: 10)
        Includes "Thesis on the British Situation, the Left Opposition, and the Comintern" by F. A. Ridley and H. R. Aggarwala; circular letters by Leon Trotsky and others; flyers; British internal discussion bulletins; "Unity and Peace Agreement"
      - Chinese section, 1932-1937 (Folder 14: 11)
        Includes Five Years of the Left Opposition in China and "On the Peasant War and the Economic Revival" by Niel Sih; circular letters and reports by Harold R. Isaacs and others; "The Present Situation and Our Tasks" by the Communist League of China
      - Cuban section, 1934 (Folder 14: 12)
        Resolutions of the Bolshevik-Leninist Party of Cuba
      - Dutch section, 1936 (Folder 14: 13)
        Includes circular letter by Dutch section
      - French section, 1930-1938 (Folder 14: 14)
        Includes circular letters and reports by Jan Frankel, Leon Trotsky and others; declaration by and reply to Jewish group in Paris; documents on "French turn" strategy; L'Organe de masse by Erwin Wolf; memorandum on conversation with Victor Serge in Paris by Melos Most
      - German section, 1931-1935 (Folder 14: 15)
        Includes circular letters by Kurt Landau and others; "The Crisis in the German Left Opposition" by Leon Trotsky; German internal discussion bulletins; flyers and leaflets
      - Spanish section, 1933-1937 (Folder 14: 16)
        Includes circular letters by Andres Nin, Leon Trotsky and others; report by Max Sterling from Spain; "Answers to Questions Concerning the Spanish Situation" by Leon Trotsky
  - International youth affiliate records, 1930-1940
    - Correspondence, 1930-1938
      Correspondents include Willy Brandt, Theo van Driesten, Georges Fux, Nathan Gould, Walter Held, and Pam Sneevliet
      - 1930-1933 (Folder 15: 1)
      - 1934 (Folder 15: 2)
      - 1935 (Folder 15: 3)
      - 1936-1938 (Folder 15: 4)
    - Internal bulletins, circa 1930s (Folder 15: 5)
      Internationale Jugendinformation no. 1-3 (1935), vol. 2 no. 2 (1936) [International Communist League]; International Bulletin no. 1 (1937) [Youth Bureau for the Fourth International]
    - Internal documents, 1934-1936
      - 1934 (Folder 15: 6)
        Mainly documents relating to the International Socialist Youth Conference held in Laren, Netherlands, and Brussels, Belgium, including "Declaration of Principles of the ICL Youth," "Resolution against Imperialist War and Militarism," "Projet de déclaration" of the Belgian youth section, "Declaration for a New Youth International," and "Zum Beschluss der Luxemburger Konferenz"; "The International Buro for Revolutionary Socialist Unity and the International Buro of Revolutionary Youth Organizations" by Walter Held; internal discussion bulletin of the International Bureau of Revolutionary Youth Organizations
      - 1935-1936 (Folder 15: 7)
        Includes circular letters and resolutions; "Bericht über die Lage im R.S.J.V.-Holland" and "ï¿½ber die Fragen des internationalen Neuaufbaus" by Theo van Driesten; incomplete typed translation of Russian publication on communist youth movement
  - Commission of Inquiry into the Charges Made against Leon Trotsky in the Moscow Trials (Dewey Commission) records, 1937, 1930-1937
    - Correspondence, 1936-1937
      Correspondents include John Dewey, Jan Frankel, Albert Goldman, Pearl Kluger, Suzanne La Follette, Felix Morrow, George Novack, Henk Sneevliet, Arne Swabeck, Leon Trotsky, Jean Van Heijenoort, and Bernard Wolfe. Includes photocopies of letters from John Dewey in Mexico to his wife
      - 1936 December-1937 April (Folder 15: 8)
      - 1937 May-October (Folder 15: 9)
    - Statements before Commission by Carleton Beals, John Dewey, Albert Goldman and Leon Trotsky, 1937 (Folder 15: 10)
    - Transcripts of selected testimony by Leon Trotsky and others. Includes 1939 Shorthand Reporter article reproducing samples of shorthand notes of testimony made by Glotzer during the hearings, 1937 (Folder 15: 11)
    - Exhibits and working materials, 1937 (Folder 15: 12)
    - Reports and press releases, 1937 (Folder 16: 1)
      Includes message by Leon Trotsky to mass protest meeting in Chicago; abstract of final Commission report; report on work of American Committee for the Defense of Leon Trotsky; press coverage and miscellany
  - Commission of Inquiry into the Charges Made against Leon Trotsky in the Moscow Trials (Dewey Commission) records, 1937, 1930-1937
    - Correspondence, 1936-1937
      - 1936 December-1937 April (Folder 15: 8)
      - 1937 May-October (Folder 15: 9)
    - Statements before Commission by Carleton Beals, John Dewey, Albert Goldman and Leon Trotsky, 1937 (Folder 15: 10)
    - Transcripts of selected testimony by Leon Trotsky and others. Includes 1939 Shorthand Reporter article reproducing samples of shorthand notes of testimony made by Glotzer during the hearings, 1937 (Folder 15: 11)
    - Exhibits and working materials, 1937 (Folder 15: 12)
    - Reports and press releases, 1937 (Folder 16: 1)
  - Unaffiliated international organization documents and issuances
    - Communist International, 1932-1939 (Folder 16: 2)
      Photocopies from Soviet archives (obtained by Glotzer in 1990s): collectivization decree, 1932; letter to Communist International from Socialist Party of America local official re popular front, 1934; clemency appeals by Nikolai Bukharin, 1938; Communist Party, U.S.A. order for copies of official Soviet history of the Soviet Communist Party, 1939
    - International Communist Opposition (Right Opposition), 1930 (Folder 16: 3)
      Internationale Nachrichten no. 1 (1930); International Information vol. 1 no. 4 (1930)
    - Labour and Socialist International, circa 1933 (Folder 16: 4)
      "The Strategy and Tactics of the International Labor Movement during the Period of Fascist Reaction," circa 1933
    - Partido Obrero de Unificación Marxista (Spain), 1936-1937 (Folder 16: 5)
      Information Bulletin two unnumbered issues, no. 4-5 (1936); The Spanish Revolution vol. 1 no. 1, 4-5 (1936), vol. 2 no. 1-3, 7 (1937)
    - Socialist Youth International, 1936 (Folder 16: 6)
      Minutes
    - Communist Party, 1934, 1936 (Folder 16: 7)
      Appeal by expellees, 1934; open letter to Socialist Party, 1936; study course outline
    - Fieldites (B. J. Field group), 1934, 1940 (Folder 16: 8)
      The Lessons of the New York Hotel Strike, 1934; statement to merger convention of Communist League of America and American Workers Party, 1934; special bulletin on Socialist Workers Party convention, 1940
    - Lovestoneites (Jay Lovestone group), 1930, 1934-1935 (Folder 16: 9)
      Youth resolution, circa 1930; Workers Age vol. 3 no. 19, 22 (1934); The Road to Communism vol. 2 no. 1-2 (1935)
    - Marlenites (George Marlen group), circa 1938 (Folder 16: 10)
      Statement to Socialist Workers Party members, circa 1938
    - Oehlerites (Hugo Oehler group), 1936-1937, 1940 (Folder 16: 11)
      Open letters to Workers Party of the United States and Socialist Party Socialist Appeal Caucus members, 1936; Barricades in Barcelona by Hugo Oehler, 1937; open letter to Socialist Workers Party convention delegates, 1940
    - Socialist Party (other than Socialist Appeal Caucus), 1933-1940
      - Minutes, 1935, 1936 November 20-22 (Folder 16: 12)
        Also includes minutes of affiliated committee for Chicago Labor May Day, 1935
      - Internal documents, 1936-1939
        - General, 1933-1939 (Folder 16: 13)
          Report of American delegation to Labour and Socialist International conference, 1933; Revolutionary Policy Committee appeal to Socialist Party membership, 1934; internal information bulletin on Austrian events, 1934; memoranda and circular letters by Irving Barshop, Norman Thomas, Gus Tyler and others re Socialist Appeal Caucus and other matters, 1936-1937; Socialist Clarity (1937 March 1); Committee to Save the Socialist Party statement, 1939
        - Committee for an Appeal Left Wing (Melos Most group), 1937 (Folder 16: 14)
          Left Wing Correspondence no. 2, 4 (1937), no. 5 (1938); Chicago Correspondence no. 1-2 (1937)
        - Marxist Policy Committee (C. Becket group) (Folder 16: 15)
          Bulletin unnumbered issue, vol. 1 no. 5-6 (1937)
    - Stammites (Tom Stamm group), 1937-1938 (Folder 16: 16)
      "The Logic of Ideas" by Tom Stamm, circa 1937; articles re Louis Basky, 1938
    - Weisbordites (Albert Weisbord group), 1934 (Folder 16: 17)
      Open letters to Communist League of America, circa 1934; The Struggle for Communism, 1934
  - Miscellany, 1932-1933, 1946-1940
    - Americana (satirical magazine edited by Alexander King, George Seldes and Georg Grosz), Apparently 1932 November-1933 April, 1933 June-July (Folder 17: 1)
      Unnumbered; dated by month but not year.
    - International Review (independent Marxist magazine published in New York), 1936-1938 (Folder 17: 2)
      Vol. 1 no. 1, 6-8 (1936), vol. 2 no. 1-4, 6, 8-9 (1937), vol. 3 no. 1, 3 (1938)
    - Miscellaneous printed matter, 1936-1940 (Folder 17: 3)
      Includes material on shorthand reporting
- Shachtmanite Period Papers, 1940-1958
  Papers of Albert Glotzer as a member of the Socialist Party and of Social Democrats, U.S.A.
  - Correspondence, 1940-1958
    Third-party letters are entered under name of writer
    - General, 1941-1958
      Includes letters by Glotzer addressed to political party bodies or to "comrades"
      - 1941-1949 (Folder 17: 4)
      - 1951-1958 (Folder 17: 5)
    - Bell, Daniel, 1954 (Folder 17: 6)
    - Burnham, James, 1940 (Folder 17: 7)
    - Clarke, George, 1946 (Folder 17: 8)
    - Cohen, Barney, 1952-1958 (Folder 17: 9)
    - Cohen, Jesse (Carlo), undated (Folder 17: 10)
    - Draper, Hal, 1947-1949 (Folder 17: 11)
    - Draper, Theodore, 1958 (Folder 17: 12)
    - Epstein, Melech, 1951 (Folder 17: 13)
    - Erber, Ernest, 1944-1946 (Folder 17: 14)
    - Farrell, James T., 1940-1948
      - 1940-1946 (Folder 17: 15)
      - 1947-1948 (Folder 17: 16)
    - Fischer, Ruth, 1946-1948 (Folder 17: 17)
      Includes typescript writing by Fischer re Gerhart Eisler
    - Geltman, Emanuel, circa 1945-1952 (Folder 18: 1)
    - Goldman, Albert, 1946-1953 (Folder 18: 2)
    - Gould, Nathan, 1947-1949 (Folder 18: 3)
    - Heisler, Francis, 1953 (Folder 18: 4)
    - Howe, Irving, circa 1945-1947 (Folder 18: 5)
    - Jacobson, Julius, 1948 (Folder 18: 6)
    - James, C. L. R., 1945 (Folder 18: 7)
    - Lauren, Stan, 1948-1956 (Folder 18: 8)
    - Macdonald, Dwight, 1945-1953 (Folder 18: 9)
    - McKinney, E. R., 1946-1947 (Folder 18: 10)
    - Magnin, Louis, 1948 (Folder 18: 11)
    - Munis, Grandizo, 1946 (Folder 18: 12)
    - Novack, George, 1947 (Folder 18: 13)
    - Plastrik, Stanley, 1944-1952 (Folder 18: 14)
    - Sara, Henry, 1945 (Folder 18: 15)
    - Schaar, John H., 1958 (Folder 18: 16)
    - Schulkind, Adelaide (League for Mutual Aid), 1957-1958 (Folder 18: 17)
    - Sedova, Natalia, 1945-1957 (Folder 18: 18)
      Includes biographical notes on Natalia Sedova by Max Shachtman
    - Shachtman, Max and Yetta, 1943-1958
      - 1943-1947 (Folder 18: 19)
      - 1948-1958 (Folder 18: 20)
    - Solano, Wilebaldo (Partido Obrero de Unificación Marxista [Spain]), 1952 (Folder 18: 21)
    - Stamm, Tom, 1946-1948 (Folder 18: 22)
      Includes typescript writing by Stamm
    - Thomas, Norman, 1957 (Folder 18: 23)
    - Wechsler, James A., 1952 (Folder 18: 24)
    - Weinrib, Max, 1958 (Folder 18: 25)
    - Widick, B. J., 1946-1958 (Folder 18: 26)
    - Willingham, Calder, 1947-1948 (Folder 18: 27)
    - Wittfogel, Karl A., 1954-1955 (Folder 18: 28)
  - Speeches and writings by Albert Glotzer, 1941-1958, undated